<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-05T13:39:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Nathan Barham</title><subtitle>Home of the Alora's Tear fantasy novel series and the personal, political and philosophical writings of author Nathan Barham.</subtitle><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><entry><title type="html">Critically Speaking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critically Speaking" /><published>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically%20Speaking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html">&lt;p&gt;While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast &lt;em&gt;Critically Speaking&lt;/em&gt; which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;ShoutEngine&lt;/a&gt; if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise has us taking on a piece of videogames journalism each week, looking for meaning and providing commentary on the state of the industry. In addition, we talk about our current obsessions in gaming and generally laugh and have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, each episode has components that are evergreen and some that are very dated. Scott is hilarious and worth a listen just for his spontaneous accents, and the recording production quality is quite high, mostly thanks to our producer/editor Ryan Taylor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the trip down memory lane at your own (quite minimal) risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;Critically Speaking with Nate Barham and Scott Boren&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast Critically Speaking which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at ShoutEngine if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/site/testing/2018/05/13/First-Post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Post" /><published>2018-05-13T15:29:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-13T15:29:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/site/testing/2018/05/13/First-Post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/site/testing/2018/05/13/First-Post.html">&lt;p&gt;Starting a new website is quite the difficult challenge when also working on a new book, but I think that the revamp will be worth the effort in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, the new solution is free. And though I love Squarespace. I think it’s time that I own the content that I’m producing on a broader level. That means designing the site, knowing its ins and outs, and hosting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I’d like the site to be fast (one of the major drawbacks of Squarespace, IMO). The best way to do that is with a static site like the new BarhamInk.com and &lt;a href=&quot;http://natebarham.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;unlike Think Critical&lt;/a&gt; and the old BarhamInk.com which were hosted on Tumblr and Squarespace, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Starting a new website is quite the difficult challenge when also working on a new book, but I think that the revamp will be worth the effort in the end.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Social Pressures of being “Right”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-Right.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Social Pressures of being &quot;Right&quot;" /><published>2016-04-24T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-04-24T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-%22Right%22</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-Right.html">&lt;p&gt;Do you like Apple’s Retina MacBook? Do you still enjoy wearing an Apple Watch every day? Maybe you like the look of Tesla’s upcoming Model 3 or use your iPad Pro as a full-fledged computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop me if you’ve heard this one before, but you’re wrong. Wrong for liking things that others don’t, wrong for attempting to understand where these designs and products are coming from rather than critiquing the obvious compromises they’ve made or the places where they’ve actually chosen to diverge from the herd, wrong, wrong, wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe wrong, as long as the future plays out a certain way and those spouting constant criticism turn out to be right (even a broken clock…). And what is right? Is it vindication in finding a MacBook five years from now that’s much faster and has much better battery life? If so, the great online advisors can claim the win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“See, we told you v1 was underpowered and had terrible battery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, “See, we told you that Tesla would have to change that no-grille design if they wanted to sell more cars.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is, they have merely predicted the inevitable. Computers will get faster, cars will have different visual touches, tablet operating systems will become more capable. Meanwhile, many must sit back and watch as the collective club nods sagely at each other for fear of ending up being the one who was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For being the one who liked Apple Watch 1.0, they will suffer the future torment of “I told you so.” And then won’t they feel dumb? After all, isn’t the most important thing to appear smart? Turns out (TM), you can be smart and disagree with the crowd. You can be insightful, and not correctly predict the future. And more essentially, simply by offering a different viewpoint, you can create a much more interesting discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I encouraging vehement Mac vs. PC era arguments? No. Am I saying that the conventional wisdom of a few high profile voices is always wrong? No. But the discourse suffers from the fear of being in the out group, the fear of having a dissenting opinion. If we were all wrong a little more often, we’d have a much more varied conversation and foster inclusivity at a basic level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ll say it. I think all of these products are great, intriguing, and worthy of discussion from many viewpoints, not just criticisms of their most obvious compromises. And none of them are perfect. None are above criticism, but they are above only criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think the same, you should not be afraid to say so, because understanding why something is the way it is informs us of the reality in which we live and not a fantasy where we get to design a world we would prefer. After all, we don’t study the horse only to say that it is not a unicorn, and that if evolution (or deity) had only included a three-foot horn on the horse’s forehead, it would have been an acceptable creature. Instead we understand the beauty of the thing as it is, what evolutionary steps may have led to its current form, and maybe every so often wonder if the unicorn is out there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unicorn becomes part of the larger understanding, just as our wished-for versions of iOS or a Mac Pro with gaming GPUs should be a part. Speculate, certainly. Criticize, of course. But don’t forget that the larger part of the fun is to analyze and thus further understand the things we are interested in. Stop caving to the social pressure of being right. Be reasonable, be considerate, but worry more about appreciating the thing before leveling the same criticism that a half-dozen full-time pundits have already articulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ok. Appreciation is not equivalent to inferior intellect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Do you like Apple’s Retina MacBook? Do you still enjoy wearing an Apple Watch every day? Maybe you like the look of Tesla’s upcoming Model 3 or use your iPad Pro as a full-fledged computer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bicycles and Backdoors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/03/04/Bicycles-and-Backdoors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bicycles and Backdoors" /><published>2016-03-04T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-03-04T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/03/04/Bicycles%20and%20Backdoors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/03/04/Bicycles-and-Backdoors.html">&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs famously called the computer a “bicycle for the mind,” an extension of ourselves that would not only make life easier, but improve it. And although the idea began with the Macintosh, the device closest to this particular Jobs ideal didn’t arrive in earnest until the iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iPhone is the computer for everyone, the one we can all use without an instruction manual and without extensive training. We use it in line at the DMV and as we wait for the water to boil; we use it at the breakfast table and (though it might be a bit crass) on the toilet. It is a part of us, it is us. We work and we play on it, ask it questions when we don’t know the answers, even send photos and communications we’d be embarrassed by were they ever let into the light of day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t let you know what I say to my wife in the privacy of our bedroom, though if you had a warrant and a surveillance team, I suppose you could listen. But even more than that — more than that — I’d never let you read my mind, let you know what I don’t even choose to tell her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve was right. This little computer is a bicycle for the mind, but not in that it lets me do things faster and more efficiently (it does that, too). It’s an extension of the mind, a part of it, an inextricably intertwined augmentation of our thoughts. The iPhone (and the smartphone in general) lets me store more thoughts, remember moments more often and more vividly, and it is able to do so because I trust it. I trust that my musings and photos and videos are safe there. And more and more as time goes on, this has become true.
It’s not a fetishization, Mr. President, it’s a fact. The contents of my phone, and other devices where I store things that I have yet to elect to share with the world — and may, in fact, never share — are private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These unshared thoughts, imaginings, creations are just that: unshared.
They are private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no. Not you, not your three letter organizations, not anyone has a right to see them if I’ve decided that they are so. Take them by force if you can, legislate if you must (and you should), but don’t leverage the locksmith as if it’s his responsibility to let you in. He doesn’t have a right to it either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This device is a digital extension of my mind, a container for my thoughts, a memory of more precise capacity and greater longevity, a secret part of who I am, that I may open to you if I so choose. There is a key, but like the one for my biological mind, I and only I am the single person who may use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one — not even the President of the United States — has a right to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you read my mind if you had the chance? Is that where this ends? I thought that we had the right to remain silent, to withhold that which would incriminate us. Do we have that right? Or will it dissolve as soon as it becomes technically feasible to circumvent it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The particular phone you want to access today may not have been an extension of its user’s mind. But the key that will unlock it would unlock mine and my wife’s and someday my children’s. It would open a door for actors from less benevolent governments, if only enough to slip in the steel toe of a combat boot. And as we know, once a crack has opened, any number of plague ridden vermin will find it. It is a matter of time, an outcome so certain that decades of research and billions of dollars have only just been able to stave it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, though I have the right to remain silent, I choose to say this: many have claimed that this case is not about one phone (the government seems to see it otherwise). I will contradict them, arguing that it is about precisely this one phone because one is all. By opening one, you’ve opened them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By weakening one, you weaken us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Steve Jobs famously called the computer a “bicycle for the mind,” an extension of ourselves that would not only make life easier, but improve it. And although the idea began with the Macintosh, the device closest to this particular Jobs ideal didn’t arrive in earnest until the iPhone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Writing Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/writing/2014/07/18/Writing-Process.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Writing Process" /><published>2014-07-18T09:18:55-07:00</published><updated>2014-07-18T09:18:55-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/writing/2014/07/18/Writing-Process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/writing/2014/07/18/Writing-Process.html">&lt;p&gt;When I’m not writing books, I spend my days teaching about them. One of my favorite courses each year is Creative Writing (obvious!). Every once in a while a student will ask how I go about my own writing. I’ve collected a few notes here to that effect. Following this list certainly doesn’t guarantee your writing will be good, or even that mine is. These are just some of the patterns I used to get from hundreds words to hundreds of thousands (Yes, &lt;em&gt;Fragments &lt;/em&gt;is technically tens of thousands, 57,000 if you’re looking for any level of accuracy, but it’s not the only book, now is it?). Here they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6380&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-daily&quot;&gt;Write Daily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few writers who would question this first bit of advice. Whether the analogy is to a muscle that needs exercise to grow stronger or to a practiced skill such as musical scales, one’s word hoard (if you’re Beowulf) needs to be accessed frequently to do it’s best work. It’s easy to tell yourself that words aren’t flowing on a particular day, but the important thing is to put pen to paper (or fingers to keys) anyway. Write even if it’s bad. Write even when a page takes you an hour. Write something different if what you planned isn’t working. Just write. And then, when you’ve written something. Feel free to walk away. Some days are thousand word days and some are ten thousand (and sometimes one hundred). Again. Feel free to walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-is-no-writers-block&quot;&gt;There is no writer’s block.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6385&quot;&gt;This one might be controversial, but I feel very strongly about it. If you believe that your creative mind, your human ability to express yourself, your capacity for creating beautiful art can be extinguished like a birthday candle flame, then you're right and it will—often. But, if you resist, if you find the secret passage through the wall, the tunnel under the mountain, if you drive your pickaxe into the solid rock face and pull yourself inch by treacherous inch, you'll find that what you once thought was writer's block is now only a distant memory—if you remember it at all. And on the days when you really do have to fight for every word, you will have trained yourself for the fight and not the habitual retreat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6386&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6387&quot;&gt;Don't try to plan everything.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6388&quot;&gt;If I had a nickel for every time Robert Burns's advice proved itself true, well you know. He said, &quot;the best laid plans of mice and men go often askew...&quot; and then followed it up with something darker that John Steinbeck took to a place darker still. But this initial piece carries the point for writing. You may think that your protagonist will fall in love with a certain fetching side character or that the villain will surely be defeated with all of your lovingly crafted friends still intact, but just look to the line above to see where it will get you. Plans are an excellent place to begin, an excellent place to which to return, and a terrible instruction manual with which to tell your story. If your characters are anything like the people we encounter in life, then they'll surprise you, and in so doing will hopefully surprise your audience as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6389&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6390&quot;&gt;Work in the morning.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6391&quot;&gt;This one may be even more controversial than Writer's Block. However, there is no better time in your day to write than when you first come to your senses (notice I didn't say &quot;wake up&quot; because that's a terrible idea). Most importantly this strategy gives you the fewest excuses. You only have to defeat the pull of the snooze button (no easy task, I am aware). Once you have done that—if you've set the alarm early enough, that is—you're free to make something with nothing else on your mind. If you wait until after lunch, the bills or the lawn or the TV show you missed last night will come calling. And, if you wait until the evening? Well, the distractions only grow and your energy only wanes. Attack writing with the freshest energy you can, every time you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6392&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6393&quot;&gt;Edit first thing, then follow the thread.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6394&quot;&gt;To combat the cobwebs that you might be dealing with when following the previous advice, try doing your editing before you write. I find that if I grab a cup of coffee, sit down, and reread my progress from the previous day, I usually find a handful of little changes I can make without slowing myself down too much. This strategy doubles as a way to merge with the stream of your prior work. Often I see clear breaks where writers have picked up the thread cold the following day. We don't use the same language in everyday life as we do when writing (even if your setting is contemporary and your characters are, like, super-trendy!). Give yourself a chance to wake up, a chance to remember, and maybe, just maybe, a chance to enjoy your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6395&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6396&quot;&gt;Feedback is critical, but in the end it's your story.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6397&quot;&gt;This one is tricky but true. Eventually—if you're serious about this writing thing—you have to ask someone else to read it. When they do, they will have feedback. It might be useful, overly critical, ignorant (in the best way), simple, or just damn right. In whatever way it manifests, you then must deal with it. Sometimes the answer will be to smile, nod, and file it away. If it comes up again, you might have a problem. If it turns up a third time, you most certainly do. Other feedback will make sense immediately, change your story for the better, and just generally make you want to hug the feedbacker (it's like football, right?) like you're the abominable snowman and she (or he) is Bugs Bunny (&quot;I will pat him and pet him and call him George.&quot; Speaking of Steinbeck). Like it says above, in the end you decide what the story is, what happens next, who lives, who dies, who falls in love, and on and on. Just know, that in your decisions you can and will be wrong. Plot twists will fall flat. Scenes will drag. Characters will say too much, or too little. When you make these decisions, do your best to hear what your readers are saying. After all, without them what do you have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;yui_3_17_2_1_1405700307931_6398&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">When I’m not writing books, I spend my days teaching about them. One of my favorite courses each year is Creative Writing (obvious!). Every once in a while a student will ask how I go about my own writing. I’ve collected a few notes here to that effect. Following this list certainly doesn’t guarantee your writing will be good, or even that mine is. These are just some of the patterns I used to get from hundreds words to hundreds of thousands (Yes, Fragments is technically tens of thousands, 57,000 if you’re looking for any level of accuracy, but it’s not the only book, now is it?). Here they are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Violence and Bioshock Infinite</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming,/politics/2013/08/15/Violence-and-Bioshock-Infinite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Violence and Bioshock Infinite" /><published>2013-08-15T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-08-15T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming,/politics/2013/08/15/Violence-and-Bioshock-Infinite</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming,/politics/2013/08/15/Violence-and-Bioshock-Infinite.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Minor Spoilers for Bioshock Infinite’s opening section&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this what we are? Is this what it all comes down to: a man with a hook/ratchet/winch pulling pieces of people’s faces apart? Of course, based on seemingly random patterns, the man might cave in an enemy skull, or simply puncture it with the hook, or fail in the first attempt only to cock back and swing again until the wonderfully rendered human face no longer returns to the frame. Regardless, the result is the same. The player-controlled protagonist bloodily rampages through an intricately designed world crushing, puncturing, and ripping until enemies cease entering his field of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, add wrench, chainsaw, rifle stock, fist, fist with brass knuckles, baseball bat, what have you, and soon enough you’ve got a description that fits a staggering amount of AAA gaming titles released in the last five to ten years. Essentially it’s the formula for the modern shooter: shoot to kill, melee if you can no longer effectively shoot. The closer the enemies get, the gorier the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;written about this before&lt;/a&gt;, about how NPC’s (and enemies especially) can be viewed as little more than digital flies to be swatted in creative ways by the player. And this makes sense in games like Halo, Saints Row, or Dishonored. The player’s goal is to eliminate the enemy (or possibly, incapacitate in the case of Dishonored), to fight through a series of conflicts with a growing array of weapons and skills with which to dispatch the oncoming enemy forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in my recent play-through of Bioshock Infinite, I found myself not only shocked but repulsed by the in-your-face gore and violence—nearly to the degree of shutting the game off entirely. Of course, a laundry list of reasons kept me playing in spite of my initial reaction, but it is the moment of shock that I’ve chosen to discuss here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infinite is a first person shooter. It says so right on the box, or in the game’s Steam description. Why should I then expect anything different from the countless other shooters that flood the industry almost daily? Why was I unfazed by Halo’s Covenant multitudes or the stream of Helghast in Killzone, and yet somehow deeply unsettled by the first Columbia police officer to come into contact with Booker’s sky-hook?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast and expectation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening sequence of Infinite is similar to its predecessor: a darkened sea, a mysterious lighthouse with various mantras and maxims scattered about. Even the rain and cultish leader echo each other. But whereas the original Bioshock sends the player straight into the demolished underwater world of Rapture, where crazed splicers fling themselves at the player from the very first moments, Infinite takes its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Booker enters Colombia while its citizens are still at peace. After an eerie baptismal initiation (that arises again cleverly near the game’s conclusion), Booker emerges among the floating platforms of 1800’s Columbia, a city in the sky. Colombia’s people mill about as they prepare for a seemingly exciting annual event: the Raffle. There’s a carnival that gives the player access to Infinite’s various mechanics as a series of carnival games. Booker fires guns at cardboard cutouts of the Vox Populi, who at the time seem to be some sort of rebel gang terrorizing Colombia’s citizens. He tests out tonics, which give him magical abilities and control of the elements. He even sees a late game enemy on display as a carnival attraction. All the while, Columbia’s citizens chat and gossip, ask him questions and ignore him, eat cotton candy and peanuts, play with their children. It’s all very idyllic, with the clear undercurrent signaling some sort of coming upheaval, around which Booker’s story (and the player’s) will most certainly orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing too out-of-the-ordinary so far. We’ve got an intro, a tutorial section, and the makings of an inciting incident. It’s Gaming Plot Mechanics 101. However, unlike the first Bioshock, which introduces the player to combat through trial by fire (electrical shock, actually), Infinite continues with it’s raffle chatter and city gossip as Booker learns about vending machines, Colombia’s currency, health boosts and salts (mana) replenishers, about turret possession, and the mysterious energy that powers the city’s clockwork horse carriages. It’s all very immersive, richly detailed, and for me, downright fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all dreams end with the sleeper awakened. Colombia’s, Booker’s, and the player’s end when the tutorials and lore are exhausted, and the game’s (sometimes a little too obvious) god rays come shining down through the foliage around the Raffle stage. A crowd has gathered in anticipation, and Booker is just in time. He unsurprisingly wins the Raffle, and is presented with a choice: throw a baseball at the interracial couple who have appeared on stage (the crowd’s expected raffle reward) or to throw the ball at the announcer (the player’s rebellious option that implicitly aligns with the cultural norms of the game’s audience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the choice, Booker is instantly recognized as the False Shepard of Colombia’s prophecies and the audience turns on a dime against him. Here’s where the face-ripping comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, or brilliance depending on how you assess it, is that up to this point, the people of Colombia have seemed pleasant, polite, and good (if a bit snooty). Now, they’re clearly racist, which on its own is horrible. But does their racism merit tearing through them like so many gazelles in the lion’s jaws? Though, even that comparison would have a purpose, at least the lion eats the gazelles (not that Booker should resort to cannibalism).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may occur to some that the racists have now become enemies and thus fit under my “flies to the swatter” doctrine. Not so. In my previous examples, the Covenant are not peaceful, polite, irritatingly aristocratic ladies and gentlemen. They’re bloodthirsty, though sometimes comical, alien invaders. Ditto for the Helghast, who have their own weak attempts at humanization. Something about Colombia’s denizens is different. Something about Infinite is different. What is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast. In most games, the desire to get immediately into the action drives the player into a frenzy of shoot, reload, shoot, reload, rest before having a chance to do much of anything else. Even a game like Mass Effect has clear interaction segments and clear combat segments. In Infinite, a peaceful crowd becomes a gruesomely slaughtered string of corpses in seconds. It happens fast, and it happens to NPC’s that before the attack are humanized from the very first moment. Never are even the guards seen as threatening or aggressive until Booker decides to throw the ball. Any more human and Ken Levine and his team might have convinced me to not even play their game at all. How’s that for “Would you kindly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though contrast does a great deal of the work in setting up the strikingly violent moments after the Raffle, in my case, expectation did the rest. Quite a long time has passed, and a good many titles, since Bioshock (or even the forgettable Bioshock 2). Those games are both well-steeped in gore. Rapture, where the first two games are set, however, is already a bloody mess when the player character arrives. Compound those two details and the expectation is that the protagonist will be adding to the violence that preceded him. Colombia, on the other hand, is clean; we’re talking Disney clean. Everything glows or shines, the clothes are indicative of upper class and the trappings of financial excess. Not only that, but the opening includes no true combat tutorials (just the seemingly innocuous carnival games). Add that to the distance between titles, and a chance to forget just how gory the Bioshock games are, and you have the makings for a stomach churning moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bioshock’s Atlas reveal and the ensuing gameplay segment are powerful but ring of the M. Night Shyamalan school of pulling the rug out from under the audience. Infinite achieves something equally as interesting, if not more so. Under the right circumstances the game evokes an emotional and visceral (as in, gut-wrenching) response early enough that the player might reject the experience all together. And if not that, the observant player is forced to come to grips with Booker’s extremely aggressive tendency toward violence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Minor Spoilers for Bioshock Infinite’s opening section</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ties that Band</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/education,/music/2013/03/24/The-Ties-that-Band.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ties that Band" /><published>2013-03-24T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-03-24T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/education,/music/2013/03/24/The-Ties-that-Band</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/education,/music/2013/03/24/The-Ties-that-Band.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article first appeared in &lt;a href=&quot;http://the-magazine.org&quot;&gt;The Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, Issue 8.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in November, I decided to try my luck with a pitch to The Magazine. I had an idea I thought would work well, and the experience to write the story. Glenn and Marco liked the idea. Here is the full article as it appeared in &lt;a href=&quot;http://the-magazine.org/8/the-ties-that-band&quot;&gt;Issue 8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ties-that-band&quot;&gt;The Ties That Band&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby is struggling. In rehearsal after rehearsal, Toby can’t seem to pull it together. He’s not keeping his toes up, not keeping his back straight, not playing the right notes. It seems like a lot to remember, but he will have to achieve it all in order to march in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/user/prideofclarkston&quot;&gt;Pride of Clarkston Marching Band and Color Guard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff takes turns following him from set to set, helping him count as he tries to play the music from memory; there are no music stands attached to instruments in a competition band. His shoulders slump, his instrument bell dips to one side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby’s my project. There are always a few. As assistant director of the marching band, I need to help Toby (a composite of many students I’ve worked with) and all 70-some other marchers break through their difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…17, 18, 19, 20!” I shout, as we near the next transition. In this move, Toby has to change direction from forward to backward. It sounds easy, but the body control required takes immense focus, especially for a 14-year-old high school freshman. Timing must be precise, with the size of each step measured and equal. Any variation can undermine the integrity of the drill design. The smallest error means judges take points off in the marching and maneuvering category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Director Bill Legg stops the band, and I catch up with Toby. An iPhone glows in my hand with the drill set’s series of overlapping arcs. I point to Toby’s coordinate. “Did you see that?” I ask. “Twenty-four counts, prep, and go. You got that part right. Next time you have to keep playing. And keep your bell up. And smaller steps, so that you hit your mark.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do the move a few more times. The first is a disaster for Toby; now he’s thinking too hard. Music, step size, counting — it all falls apart. But we rehearse it again and again. The fourth time, it’s much better. His feet lock into position with the authority of a drill sergeant, and I cheer him on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s perfect. You nailed it that time!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby grins. Yeah, it’s better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;band-ten-hut&quot;&gt;Band, Ten-Hut!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prideofclarkston.com/&quot;&gt;Pride of Clarkston&lt;/a&gt;, an 80-piece marching band from a small-town high school in southeastern Washington, has competed around the state for more than 30 years. Band traditions date back decades — more than a century for marching bands — but two years ago, ours took a decidedly modern turn. I began using my iPhone to manage drill-charts and count sequences. Now, iOS devices are the staff’s primary tools for recording, monitoring, tuning, and teaching the band’s students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer, the band retreats to Camp Wooten, a wooded site along the waters of the Tucannon River, where for 33 years the season’s first rehearsals have taken place. During a three-day stint at camp, the band learns how to march (it’s not just walking in time), how to find their coordinates (the precise locations in which they should stand to create legible shapes for the audience), and how to move between those points, all while playing an instrument and focusing their eyes on the stands rather than the ground beneath their feet. Some make an easy start of it, but most will stumble and recover. Nearly all come away with an invigorating sense of accomplishment and teamwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only three years ago, the Pride had a blanket “no cellphone” policy during rehearsals, be it during camp or back home. Screens meant distraction and disconnect from the unity of the group. Today, when the phones come out, they have a different purpose: They’re tools instead of toys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer retreat, the army of volunteers affectionately dubbed “the Band Parents” gets involved, too. Pacing up and down formations with iPads, iPods, and iPhones — and possibly some Android devices — parents and staff spend the day capturing clips of the Pride’s performers in action. Later, on the screen set up at the back of the tin-roofed mess hall, student after student marches past. Some are splendid examples and others not so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band members watch with rapt attention as their digital selves glide over the field. They critique their own posture and execution while applauding newcomers to whom marching seems like second nature. At the next rehearsal, groups of students are on the field early, working to improve what they’ve seen in the video. Again the staff and parents film, and again the students watch, and again the band improves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;forward-glide&quot;&gt;Forward, Glide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in Clarkston, I squint and angle the phone screen away from my face. It’s bright out, but I can still read the conversation. It’s from the Band Instructors Facebook group, where our preparations for rehearsal often begin. Everyone agrees: We have a &lt;em&gt;march-style&lt;/em&gt; problem to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March-style is the specific set of rules that the band uses to define how each member should traverse the field. For instance, Clarkston uses a rolled-toe forward march and an on-the-toes backward march. When a performer moves across the field, his or her shoulders must stay parallel to the sideline while feet point in the direction of travel — imagine a tank’s turret versus its tracks. Marchers’ posture must be straight-backed, with their weight forward and their instrument elevated so that they appear to be playing into the stadium press box instead of the sideline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All bands have a march-style problem; it’s part of learning the skill. However, this rehearsal has particular challenges. Not only do we have march style to fix, we have music memorization, musicality, choreography, and a lot of cleaning up to make sure that the shapes on the field look like arcs and lines instead of illegible blobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We break the rehearsal into blocks, deciding how much time we should spend on each technique as well as on each section of the show. The schedule goes into our smartphones so that each staff member has quick access to what will be happening next, and so we don’t get mired in any one section or technique. With the schedule finished, it’s out to the field for rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dress-set-dress&quot;&gt;Dress Set, Dress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the three months following camp, the band learns an entire show, performs it in front of an audience or a panel of judges (or both), and then takes the critique back to the practice field to make improvements. The band’s staff members rely on phones and tablets and laptops to support almost every adjustment we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the end of the season, the band visits Auburn, Washington, for its final competition. After the daylong bus ride, the students scurry out at the Westfield Southcenter in Tukwila. From a seat in a newly opened burrito eatery, the staff adds one last iOS touch to an already heavy touchscreen season: a scavenger hunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a group-texting app, students exchange messages with the staff. First to take a photo of an item costing more than $100? A shot from the neighboring Guitar Center comes back. Okay, then. First photo of an item over $5000? A picture appears from the Smart car display in front of the food court. How about video of the most students doing the ballad choreography? Three videos pop out, one with the students in flying V formation and a conductor leading them. They lean and sway, slide and bow, click their heels, and sing the music as confused shoppers pass by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all in fun and brings the students together even when they are spread out across hundreds of thousands of square feet. The scavenger hunt  is what they’ll remember, but the staff knows the real reason for the texts: Every student must be with a group that has a smartphone. Almost all of them have one; those who don’t pair up with those who do. When it comes time to gather the scattered students, a text goes out. Everyone gets to the bus, and no one has to stand around waiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to find even more ways to use the technology, from sound mixing to rehearsal tracks to synthetic sounds. The Band Parents want to buy a high-quality audio system to bring Clarkston further into the modern era of marching band. Many schools already use electronic instruments in their pit percussion sections, and one or two of the Pride’s higher-division competitors even mix and sample sounds using iPads. When the new system arrives, there will be an iPad at the ready in Clarkston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;band-dismissed&quot;&gt;Band, Dismissed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing their final competition performance of the year, the Pride exits the field with smiles on their faces and light in their eyes. One of the smiles is Toby’s. His step size was perfect, with his toes rolling on forward march and his heels high in backward march. He and the rest of the band have just performed the best version of the show to date, and they can feel it. The crowd can feel it, too. For the second time in three years, the Pride wins the Spirit of Auburn People’s Choice Award at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://auburnveteransday.webs.com&quot;&gt;Veterans Day Marching Band Championships&lt;/a&gt;. On the way to the photography area, students high-five and embrace in teary-eyed hugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they climb the bleachers, one voice rises from the group, singing a steady, muffled note. Another adds to the sound, and then another. Soon, the whole band is singing a major chord. One senior, the band’s drum major, sings the original note two octaves higher in a lilting falsetto. When the photographer cuts them off, the band grins back for the camera. Singing isn’t usually scored in marching band, but togetherness is. Smartphones still aren’t allowed in performance uniforms, and so the moment remains in memories alone. Some things were meant to stay analog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">This article first appeared in The Magazine, Issue 8.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mass Effect’s Ending</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/09/09/Mass-Effect's-Ending.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mass Effect's Ending" /><published>2012-09-09T03:57:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-09-09T03:57:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/09/09/Mass-Effect's-Ending</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/09/09/Mass-Effect's-Ending.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spoilers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to understand Mass Effect’s conclusion, you have to start not at the beginning, but at the end, the very end. After the credits roll, an old man—and a child who appears to be his grandson—stand in a grove of trees looking out onto a spectacular night sky. The child listens in wonder as the grandfather finishes Mass Effect’s narrative, then asks if the grandfather will tell him another story about “the Shepherd.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In creating a series that spans hundreds of choices, a spectrum of &lt;em&gt;morality&lt;/em&gt; decisions, battles in which any number of characters can die, and various overall design adjustments, Mass Effect manages to finish with a coherent epilogue that encompasses all possible narrative conclusions. Beyond the color-coded final choice offered to Commander Shepard at the pinnacle of the transformed citadel-plus-crucible device, whether you played before or after the expanded ending, the Mass Effect universe ends the same: life goes on, and Commander Shepard was the key piece in deciding how that life would continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the grandfather epilogue provides a meaningful connection back to the single most-repeated word over the course of dozens of hours of gameplay: Shepard. Think about all the times you heard that name. Remember the YouTube videos that compiled characters saying it again and again. And whether it’s superficial or not, the connection to the epilogue’s Shepherd—the protector—cannot be taken for granted. &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; Commander Shepard would become was decided before the player even presses start at the first game’s opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;But it takes away player agency at the last moment!&lt;/em&gt;” you cry. Perhaps it does, but weren’t you paying attention as all those hours of dialogue, cutscenes, and Codex entries rolled by? Races in the Mass Effect universe have only the illusion of choice. Everything goes back to the inevitable cycle which ends with the coming of the Reapers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;But I chose to wipe out all synthetics!&lt;/em&gt;” you say. That’s all well and good for you, but according to the narrative content (which you only ignore if you’re under the delusion that you are making the story, not experiencing a story authored by someone else) synthetic life will again reemerge when a technologically advanced race &lt;em&gt;invents it&lt;/em&gt;. So there it is, cyclical thinking, just as the game narrative has presented from day one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there other ways the designers could have concluded the trilogy, yes. Could the voice acting have been better in the epilogue, certainly. But it is the epilogue that finishes Mass Effect, not the choice of Commander Shepard (or the player). The series, it seems, strives to make two points concerning the end of its narrative. The first is that even in a veritable universe’s worth of decisions, all choices lead to the same eventual end. The second is that choice defines character, and character is more important than events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the grandfather tells the story to his grandson, when the events of Mass Effect have become tales from long ago, it is not &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; happened in the story that matters but &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Spoilers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UI and Achievements</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/07/10/UI-and-Achievements.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UI and Achievements" /><published>2012-07-10T04:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-07-10T04:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/07/10/UI-and-Achievements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/07/10/UI-and-Achievements.html">&lt;p&gt;Shards of glass rain down from overhead, spattering and clinking in the glow of roiling flames. Beneath your feet, the ground shakes, jostling your view. Beyond the shrapnel and blurring vibrations, a trusted friend hangs on the edge of the precipice. Someone you’ve spent hours helping, training, and conversing with. At one point, it even seemed the two of you might have a romantic interest in one another, only to discover that you make a better team without the baggage of such entanglements. Now she hangs, fingers scraping helplessly through the debris of the collapsing environment, struggling for purchase. She’s saved your ass a hundred times; now it’s your turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you burn everything, unload all the ammo on the surrounding enemies, expend every resource to reach her in time. The twisting metal and crumbling bedrock shudder again, knocking you off balance and her hand free from the edge. And just before she drops out of frame, the two hands clasp and you wrench her up from the chasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Showering sparks and fragments of structure tumble all around. Your hand remains entwined with hers as you race for the exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thanks,” she says with a smile that you return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And fade to black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;boo-deep!&lt;/em&gt; “Achievement Unlocked: A Friend in Need”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all seen it, played it. Forgive my scenario, or use it to understand my next point. If that moment had any emotional impact, the sound and invasive UI element shattered it. And for what? A digital trophy or arbitrary allotment of equally arbitrary points. Why? So that we can compare gaming accomplishments against our friends or random Internet encounters? Any value in the narrative interactions of characters and environment and plot are reduced to a system notification and point value. Pitiful. Achievements—and the UI nightmares used to present them—are a plague on the progression of video games as a respectable form of art, and one of the single most disruptive elements to immersion in current games design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As readers of this site know, I do not try to play every game that comes out, nor could I afford to (by cost of time or money) if I wanted to. I expect to enjoy each gaming experience as much as possible. But when my adventure in deep space is interrupted by that &lt;em&gt;boo-deep!&lt;/em&gt; and garish green overlay, I cringe and even get a little bit angry. Then, when I’m hacking away at thousands of demons or zombies, a giant red spatter of UI slops its way onscreen to notify me that I have, in fact, just killed a thousand zombies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neat. I could sorta tell that by the, you know, dead zombies, but whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can’t decide is whether my current annoyance with achievements has to do more with the reduction of in-game (especially narrative) milestones to mere status updates or that UI’s in games have become so large, so screen dominating and full of constant streams of usually meaningless information, that the actual content of the game becomes buried under layer after (sometimes overlapping) layer of rewards and !’s and ?’s and &lt;em&gt;boo-deep&lt;/em&gt;’s. Either way, the game and its characters seem to be getting farther and farther away from the player while the achievement UI gets closer and closer, larger and larger, louder and louder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a while, I thought all of this was going to the wayside in favor of cleaner, simpler UI’s that would get out of the player’s way. I thought that designers had realized that achievements should stick mainly to mechanics mastery; easter-egg discovery; or endgame, large-number accomplishments. Apparently designers have yet to agree that this is the better direction. Instead, I get character dialogue telling me that the threat has been vanquished, a quest reward UI gewgaw showing my experience and gold gain, and a poster-sized achievement graphic overlapping it all saying little more than “Threat Vanquished!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now many readers will, I’m sure, direct me to the large number of indie games that eschew UI and achievements in just the sort of way I seem to be requesting. But that’s not who has the problem to begin with, and (for better or worse) it’s not the part of the industry that will be visible from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we like it or not, AAA games are the face of the industry, and thus the face of the art-form. If video games are to be recognized as a higher form of entertainment, the adjustments have to start at the Mass Effect, Call of Duty, and Diablo levels. While the operating system and application industry moves closer to simple interfaces and clean designs, AAA games get more and more elements piled atop one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to make one request. Start your next game with no user interface, none at all. Then, when it’s unplayable to a new user (and it will be) add only what you cannot live without. Repeat this process until you complete a play through. At that point, remove any elements you do not &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to look at in order to finish the final parts of the game. Make those optional, enabled within settings, and cal, it a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am no designer, and someone out there who does this for a living is probably laughing at my suggestion. However, the fact remains that these popups and alerts, these shiny text billboards and &lt;em&gt;boo-deep&lt;/em&gt;’s are not helping the medium. If they were all gone tomorrow, I’d say good riddance without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: For the UI portion of this article, &lt;a href=&quot;http://games.on.net/2012/07/you-know-what-i-love-diegetic-huds/&quot;&gt;Brenden Keogh&lt;/a&gt; has a great piece (written after I queued my post here, I swear) which addresses many of my issues with an over abundance of UI elements. When I wrote this, I hadn’t considered what Keogh calls the “diegetic HUD.” I’m not sure it can address my frustration with achievements, but to say the article is worth your time undersells it. Go check it out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Shards of glass rain down from overhead, spattering and clinking in the glow of roiling flames. Beneath your feet, the ground shakes, jostling your view. Beyond the shrapnel and blurring vibrations, a trusted friend hangs on the edge of the precipice. Someone you’ve spent hours helping, training, and conversing with. At one point, it even seemed the two of you might have a romantic interest in one another, only to discover that you make a better team without the baggage of such entanglements. Now she hangs, fingers scraping helplessly through the debris of the collapsing environment, struggling for purchase. She’s saved your ass a hundred times; now it’s your turn.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">There are Far Worse Terms Than Cinematic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/06/08/There-are-Far-Worse-Terms-Than-Cinematic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There are Far Worse Terms Than Cinematic" /><published>2012-06-08T04:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-06-08T04:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/06/08/There-are-Far-Worse-Terms-Than-Cinematic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2012/06/08/There-are-Far-Worse-Terms-Than-Cinematic.html">&lt;p&gt;What is a cinematic experience? For one, it’s a marketing term used on game boxes all the time. It conjures all sorts of images regarding action, intensity, and drama. That’s why they keep using it. A high rate of positive connotation is as good a reason as any for a marketer to repeatedly use a word or phrase. They want you to feel good about the purchase you’re about to make, and what better way than convincing the buyer that they will have a cinematic experience while playing the game?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over at Rock, Paper, Shotgun, Adam Smith has a piece &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2012/05/17/experiences-between-accident-and-animation/&quot;&gt;decrying the use of the term &lt;em&gt;cinematic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In it, he mostly rests the argument upon one negative connotation of word:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The cinema is cinematic but games are not, or at least they shouldn’t be, not in their entirety. An action film can contain thousands of moving parts in a scene, a drama could contain a sequence communicated through the lack of motion, but in most instances the effectiveness of both will be achieved through blocking, through choreography and rehearsal, through placement and post-production. A game allows these elements to be broken and rearranged, and for each sequence to become something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I was nodding my head in agreement. Of course we should avoid the term cinematic, games aren’t movies! Games are made up of systems and decisions and play styles. Watching a movie has none of these (though making one does). Then, I considered Smith’s chief example, the &lt;em&gt;Max Payne 3&lt;/em&gt; marketing. I don’t think that the dev team for &lt;em&gt;Max Payne&lt;/em&gt; had in mind that the experience would be the same every time—which is the definition for cinematic that Smith seems to prefer. The marketing is talking, as they so often are, about &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the marketers and designers are doing their jobs, &lt;em&gt;Max Payne&lt;/em&gt; should feel like a movie. Every time. Oh, you died and have to play this section again? It may be different, but it should &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like a director spent hours crafting it even though you were making it up as you went along. Most games like &lt;em&gt;Max Payne&lt;/em&gt; are power fantasies, and what could make the power fantasy better than a flawless performance, nail biting victory, or sloppy close-call? Making it look as though that was the way the scene was intended to be played all along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what then do we mean by cinematic? If we look at the root of gaming history we find a simple truth. Early games worked almost exclusively with fixed camera perspectives, and thus, fixed player perspectives. Sure, levels would scroll along with Mario or Link, but essentially the camera—and the player—stayed in the same place. Not so in 2012 (and maybe more importantly for this argument, not so for films in 1985).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In film, the viewer’s perspective can be almost anywhere. My view, your view, first person, top-down, wide-angle, fisheye, etc . . . . And it changes constantly. So, in a game that claims to be cinematic, the perspective should mimic some of the camerawork in film. Open up the landscape and maybe drop the UI as the first person protagonist looks over the smoking battlefield. Pull the camera out of first person as the player’s character is shot and wounded, waiting for assistance from a teammate. Show the opposing player’s view for the killcam. The list goes on. And without adding to the list, sound and music work the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, certainly long before Mario et al, cinema did the hard work of creating a visual language for the screen. Like it or not, games happen on the same conceptual screen, especially games like &lt;em&gt;Max Payne&lt;/em&gt;. Are there aspects of gaming that designers should be focusing on instead, sure, but saying that cinematic is a dirty word seems a bit like the proverbial nose cutting to spite one’s face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaming needs the mature visual language of cinema in all of its strength as well as equally strong systems with which the player can interact. Interaction is what sets games apart, and on that, Smith and I can agree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">What is a cinematic experience? For one, it’s a marketing term used on game boxes all the time. It conjures all sorts of images regarding action, intensity, and drama. That’s why they keep using it. A high rate of positive connotation is as good a reason as any for a marketer to repeatedly use a word or phrase. They want you to feel good about the purchase you’re about to make, and what better way than convincing the buyer that they will have a cinematic experience while playing the game?</summary></entry></feed>