<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-30T08:56:46-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Barham Ink</title><subtitle>Publishing</subtitle><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><entry><title type="html">Volume IV Paperbacks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/09/30/Volume-4-Paperbacks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volume IV Paperbacks" /><published>2018-09-30T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-30T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/09/30/Volume-4-Paperbacks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/09/30/Volume-4-Paperbacks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vol4/circlets paperback.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Circlets and Seekers Paperback&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud to announce that today, &lt;a href=&quot;/books/circlets and seekers.md&quot;&gt;Alora’s Tear, Volume IV: Circlets and Seekers&lt;/a&gt; is now available in paperback. They’re gorgeous, thanks to the work of cover artist Isis Sousa and are made with quality, professional grade materials. The goal is always to make my books look and feel every bit as polished as a product from a large publishing corporation. Circlets and Seekers is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to get a copy is to attend one of the events where I’ll be selling the books in person. There, the prices are the lowest ($10 for Volume IV, and no shipping!) and I can sign it right there, with your name and custom inscription. Better yet, I get to thank you face-to-face for supporting my writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you won’t be in the area, or just can’t wait, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/shop/BarhamInk&quot;&gt;Barham Ink Etsy Shop&lt;/a&gt;. Here, you can still get a custom, signed copy, for $10.99 plus shipping and it will arrive at your door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the series is also available on Amazon and other major online book retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However you get your copy, thanks so much. I hope you enjoy the first stage of Askon’s new journey, the new characters he meets, and their stories. I’ve said it before, but I’m so excited for all of you to experience it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Volume IV Release Day!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/14/Volume-4-Release.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volume IV Release Day!" /><published>2018-08-14T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-14T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/14/Volume-4-Release</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/14/Volume-4-Release.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s finally here. &lt;em&gt;Circlets and Seekers&lt;/em&gt; is available now on all the popular digital platforms!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vol4/volume 4 banner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Circlets and Seekers Banner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve followed Askon and his friends through the battle of their time, through Iramov and his dark army, through betrayal and surprise, through doubt and despair, and magic, because of course there is magic in Vladvir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the old friends return, but it is the new characters I’m most excited for you to meet. I hope you love them (and love to hate them). Their stories are just beginning. The girl from the vision awaits. They all await.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quickest way to get a copy is the digital version for $4.99. As with Trilogy One, I tried to keep it in the “coffee and a pastry” price range (though these days, it’s more like “a nice coffee if you’re lucky” range). I guarantee it lasts longer than the coffee does, even if you’re a really fast reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are all the ways you can get a copy online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://geo.itunes.apple.com/us/book/circlets-and-seekers/id1422535320?mt=11&quot;&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2OpoyzY&quot;&gt;Kindle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/circlets-and-seekers&quot;&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/circlets-and-seekers-nathan-barham/1129191454?ean=2940161699225&quot;&gt;Nook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Fear not, paperback fans, Volume IV will have a paperback edition to match the first Alora’s Tear trilogy. Unfortunately, there was an error during the proofing process which has caused a slight delay. For that reason, I’ll be holding off on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://barhamink.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt; until the paperback is available. If you’re on the list, you’ll get a note when they are ready to ship. If you’re not on the list (or can’t remember if you signed up) &lt;a href=&quot;https://barhamink.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;here’s the link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">It’s finally here. Circlets and Seekers is available now on all the popular digital platforms!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Volume IV Cover Reveal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/10/Volume-IV-Cover-Reveal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volume IV Cover Reveal" /><published>2018-08-10T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-10T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/10/Volume-IV-Cover-Reveal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/08/10/Volume-IV-Cover-Reveal.html">&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, August 14th the second Alora’s Tear trilogy begins. Today, enjoy the magnificent work of Isis Sousa and the back cover text for Volume IV, &lt;em&gt;Circlets and Seekers&lt;/em&gt;. I’m excited to share the book with all of you, next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vol4/vol 4 wrap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Circlets and Seekers Wraparound Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;circlets-and-seekers&quot;&gt;Circlets and Seekers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In artificial night she waits, alone, fears mounting as the brittle sounds of vermin scratch and scrabble through the walls. He’ll return soon, but he will bring no light. And hope? It’s been days since there was any of that. They want to know what she knows, about the Tear, about the fragments, about her father. They’ll shout, they’ll threaten, deprive her of food and sleep, but they’d surely never use the twisted tools glimpsed in passing candle flame. Not here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Tolarenz town hall, Askon thinks of nothing but the woman in the vision. His city is not itself. He is not himself. After seeing her, after using the fragments of Alora’s Tear to peer into the frozen caldera where his people entered the world, Askon knows he must go. He must brave the bitter cold and trackless snow in search of Dalkaldur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Líana and Edward, Thomas and Elise, John of Dalstone, all will be tested. Follow or stay? And if they follow, to what end? Death in icy desolation is as likely as success. And if they succeed—if they find Dalkaldur and the woman whose circlet reads “Alora”—they must then answer the most unsettling question: how did she come to possess the fragments? With Askon in the lead, and a new threat appearing across the land of Vladvir, there is only one way to be certain. They must find her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-order&quot;&gt;Pre Order&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://geo.itunes.apple.com/us/book/circlets-and-seekers/id1422535320?mt=11&quot;&gt;Apple Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2OpoyzY&quot;&gt;Kindle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/circlets-and-seekers-nathan-barham/1129191454?ean=2940161699225&quot;&gt;Nook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kobo.com/us/en/ebook/circlets-and-seekers&quot;&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">On Tuesday, August 14th the second Alora’s Tear trilogy begins. Today, enjoy the magnificent work of Isis Sousa and the back cover text for Volume IV, Circlets and Seekers. I’m excited to share the book with all of you, next week.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kit - SteelSeries Arctis 7</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/24/Arctis-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kit - SteelSeries Arctis 7" /><published>2018-07-24T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-24T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/24/Arctis-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/24/Arctis-7.html">&lt;p&gt;The future is wireless (or so they keep saying). My current PC gaming setup is now part of that future with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Jlt8w9&quot;&gt;SteelSeries Arctis 7&lt;/a&gt; headset. These headphones boast the same 40mm speaker drivers as the &lt;em&gt;pro&lt;/em&gt; model by SteelSeries, a high quality retractable microphone, and lag-free audio, all in a subtle design free of the gaudy LEDs and faux robotic nonsense that mars most gaming peripherals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SSA7/side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SteelSeries Arctis 7 Side View&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comfort&quot;&gt;Comfort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arctis 7 features a unique ski-goggle strap adjustment system for improved comfort. It’s a fine way to adjust the fit, but in practice the arc of the metal headband itself is too shallow. Regardless of the nice, infinitely resizable strap, the metal rests against my head when the strap is loose enough for the cups to comfortably cover my ears. Your milage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SSA7/cushion.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SteelSeries Arctis 7 Ear Cup Cushion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The headphone cushions use a fabric similar to modern sports equipment that supposedly makes them more breathable over long gaming sessions. I’ve found this to be mostly true, though I wish the cushions were thicker. They stay cool and don’t deteriorate like the fake leather material of cheaper headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole headset is quite light, and meets my primary goal of being more comfortable than my previous pair, the wired &lt;a href=&quot;http://toolsandtoys.net/reviews/a-razer-mega-review-blackwidow-x-tournament-keyboard-deathadder-elite-mouse-and-kraken-pro-7-1-headset/&quot;&gt;Razer Kraken Pro v2&lt;/a&gt; (a very comfortable set if you’re willing to ignore the wire).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;microphone&quot;&gt;Microphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my main complaints with the Kraken Pro v2 was the low quality microphone. I play a lot of Heroes of the Storm and enjoy doing so with friends: strategizing, calling shots, and just generally chatting. The aggressive audio processing, noise gating, and other Razer features never worked properly, and without them, the sound was harsh and difficult to tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SSA7/lighting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SteelSeries Arctis 7 Mic and Power Button Lighting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arctis 7s claim the best microphone in gaming, and though that specific assertion may be hyperbolic, it has been exactly what I was looking for in a mic. My voice sounds more true to life, the controls are simple and direct with no black-box &lt;em&gt;smart&lt;/em&gt; switches or toggles. Best of all, background noise is limited by the hardware itself simply by using good mic technique. There’s a large air conditioner next to my desk that I used to have to shut off if I wanted to be on comms, but now that same unit can kick on and off without any complaints from teammates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sound-quality&quot;&gt;Sound Quality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the audio quality realm, the Arctis 7s struggle a bit. The default configuration lacks bass and soundstage depth. However, the mid and high range are excellent, a very important point if your ear is more attuned to the subtleties of sound design. What these headphones lack in bass can easily be accounted for with a few EQ adjustments at the low end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/SSA7/controls.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SteelSeries Arctis 7 Controls&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a feature of note is the DTS surround sound support. It’s a nice-to-have, and atmospheric games are definitely enhanced by its expanded soundstage and precise positioning when listening for something coming up behind you or off in the distance to one side, but for non-first-person games, you’ll want to turn it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-and-conclusion&quot;&gt;Software and Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The configuration utility is neither excellent nor terrible. Like most software of its kind (especially in the Windows world) it simply &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. One nice feature is the ability to set configuration profiles for specific applications. For instance, in the case of a top-down isometric game like Heroes of the Storm, you can set the software to automatically switch off DTS surround and turn on microphone monitoring. Generally, updates are frequent and issues are few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a wireless headset, there’s little to dislike about the SteelSeries Arctis 7. I’ve enjoyed being untethered from my desk between rounds while still being able to hear conversations; battery life is long, to the point that it’s a non-issue; and it’s nice to know that my voice sounds more like me whether we’re talking about the latest popular TV series or the next team fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the Arctis 7 headset on &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Jlt8w9&quot;&gt;Amazon for around $150&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">The future is wireless (or so they keep saying). My current PC gaming setup is now part of that future with the SteelSeries Arctis 7 headset. These headphones boast the same 40mm speaker drivers as the pro model by SteelSeries, a high quality retractable microphone, and lag-free audio, all in a subtle design free of the gaudy LEDs and faux robotic nonsense that mars most gaming peripherals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kit - Recommendations and Reviews</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/23/Kit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kit - Recommendations and Reviews" /><published>2018-07-23T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-23T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/23/Kit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/kit/2018/07/23/Kit.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things included in the 2018 redesign of &lt;a href=&quot;barhamink.com&quot;&gt;BarhamInk.com&lt;/a&gt; is a place for gear recommendations and product reviews. I love technology and have written extensively about it on Think Critical, but I’ve also contributed thousands of words and dozens of product photos to sites like the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://toolsandtoys.net/author/natebarham/&quot; title=&quot;Tools &amp;amp; Toys Author Page for Nate Barham&quot;&gt;Tools &amp;amp; Toys&lt;/a&gt;, the Magazine, and The Loop Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these were fantastic opportunities and excellent experiences which I greatly enjoyed. From time to time, I’d like to continue sharing my experiences with new devices, peripherals, software, and accessories, here, the new home for all of my writing online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, I’ll be beginning a new series of posts called “Kit.” It’s a simple title prefix that signals to readers they’ll be reading a product review. The first of these will go live tomorrow. Here’s what to look forward to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My thoughts on a product with a focus on details that don’t make it into the marketing pages. Do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; expect a rewrite of what you can already find on the manufacturer’s website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photography that shows what the shipped item looks like in the real world. Expect 3-5 clear, high quality shots that give a good sense of the materials and construction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An affiliate link through which you can purchase the item (where available). These links ensure that I receive a small commission (from Amazon, Apple, or whomever) if you buy one of the items I’ve recommended. It is not my intent to make these posts into a significant revenue stream, but if you choose to buy something on a recommendation from this site, I hope you’ll use the links provided to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the new “Kit” post category on the 2018 redesign of BarhamInk.com. I look forward to sharing lots of cool stuff with you in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">One of the things included in the 2018 redesign of BarhamInk.com is a place for gear recommendations and product reviews. I love technology and have written extensively about it on Think Critical, but I’ve also contributed thousands of words and dozens of product photos to sites like the excellent Tools &amp;amp; Toys, the Magazine, and The Loop Magazine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Volume IV Title</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volume IV Title" /><published>2018-06-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title.html">&lt;p&gt;This summer, the second trilogy in the &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; series begins. For today, let’s start with the title to book four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Alora's Tear, Volume IV:&lt;br /&gt;
Circlets and Seekers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you’ve read the Epilogue to &lt;em&gt;The Voice like Water&lt;/em&gt;. I’m so excited to share this story with everyone. Check back for more details, back cover text, excerpt, and of course the fantastic cover art!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">This summer, the second trilogy in the Alora’s Tear series begins. For today, let’s start with the title to book four.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Site Design 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site Design 2018" /><published>2018-06-14T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-14T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018.html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the redesigned &lt;a href=&quot;http://barhamink.com&quot;&gt;BarhamInk.com&lt;/a&gt;, the new home for &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; and other writings by me, Nathan Barham. For most people, the take away is this: it’s fast! Like, really fast. Even if you’re on a limited mobile connection, BarhamInk.com should be one of the fastest sites you visit on any given day. And despite the speed increase, all of the content, features, and capabilities from the old site are still here (plus a lot more). If you’ve been following the book series since its debut in 2014 or if you’ve been following my writing on Apple, gaming, and other interests, you’ll notice more changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, where once there were two sites, now there is only one. When I began writing &lt;a href=&quot;natebarham.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Think Critical&lt;/a&gt; (at natebarham.com) my goal was simply to share my thoughts about technology and gaming, two interests that have been a part of my life for as long as I can remember. I hosted the site with Tumblr, and though it never really fit the trademark Tumblr aesthetic, there was enough customization that I could make the site look and behave almost exactly as I envisioned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I published &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear: Fragments&lt;/em&gt;, and with it, BarhamInk.com on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.squarespace.com&quot;&gt;Squarespace&lt;/a&gt;. This solution allowed me to focus on content first, things like &lt;a href=&quot;/locations/&quot;&gt;important locations&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;/pronunciation/&quot;&gt;pronunciation guide&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/writing/2014/07/18/Writing-Process/&quot;&gt;thoughts on writing&lt;/a&gt;. Not to mention links for buying books and information about the new publishing entity I’d just created. Secondarily, Squarespace provided easy design templates to work with that didn’t require CSS or HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward several years—and four novels. Things have changed. Now everything points to BarhamInk.com, one site to communicate my thoughts on various subjects as well as promote and enrich the world of Vladvir, its characters, and any future worlds when Askon and friends turn their final page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who have seen all the iterations of my online writing presence, I thank you especially. Without the readers of Think Critical, I might not have felt confident enough to publish &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; on my own. And for those who have always followed the books but never knew about the site that came before, it is my hope that you will enjoy having a more complete picture of the &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt; who crafted Askon’s tale and all the tales yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Technical site details follow, if you’re into that sort of thing…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;readability&quot;&gt;Readability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of years ago I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://practicaltypography.com&quot;&gt;Butterick’s Practical Typography&lt;/a&gt;. It was the first formal consolidation of all the typography principles I was seeing applied across many of my favorite sites on the web, some of which are still actively maintained today (&lt;a href=&quot;http://brooksreview.net&quot;&gt;The Brooks Review&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgemmell.com&quot;&gt;MattGemmell.com&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://inessential.com&quot;&gt;Inessential&lt;/a&gt; by Brent Simmons, &lt;a href=&quot;http://macstories.net&quot;&gt;MacStories&lt;/a&gt;, and many others). I used these principles in designing the paperback versions of &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; and have done so on BarhamInk.com as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of device, text should be large, clear and high contrast, with ample whitespace between lines and surrounding the content, while line length balances screen size with typeface size, never extending so far that they become tiring for readers. These details alone aim to make a better reading experience whether you’re visiting for a chapter-length excerpt or a blog post of a few dozen words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The featured typeface is Quattrocento (in its serif and sans versions) to characterize the site’s text in a way that suggests both general purpose writing and medieval fantasy (when reading Vladvir-related content). If you block web fonts, you’ll get Palatino, Garamond, or just plain old serif. And, because I was too attached to it, despite examining dozens of alternatives, Adelle makes its way over from Think Critical for the site title courtesy of TypeKit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links and headings take on my favorite shade of green (Askon’s signature cloak is the same color for both practical and sentimental reasons), differentiating them from body text and navigation links. All links take on the underline text decoration when you hover over them with the cursor. Pretty standard, of course, but intentional nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;images&quot;&gt;Images&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images take on several forms, most notably the large, highly detailed art from &lt;a href=&quot;http://artstation.com/isissousa&quot;&gt;Isis Sousa&lt;/a&gt;, whose work is as much a part of the &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; series as are my words. These big beautiful digital paintings take center stage, setting the tone for each volume’s preview page. Inside posts, images are smaller and can flow alongside the text on the desktop or tablet, while remaining inline on phone screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigation&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigation links are persistent across the site,but do not follow the reader (I despise sites that do this) as they scroll down the page. On desktop, each category has the ability to show a dropdown submenu for more options. For instance, the about section has a dropdown for The Author, Barham Ink, and The Site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On mobile, there’s one link to buy books and a menu that takes readers to the main sections of the site, the submenu links from the desktop dropdown are provided above the content so mobile users don’t miss out on any of the content suggestions from the desktop version. Lastly, a second set of navigation appears below the featured image on book buying pages to highlight the places where you can purchase &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; in paperback and ebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;responsive-design&quot;&gt;Responsive Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world where most people consider their phone to be their primary computer (even if they don’t know it consciously) websites should present themselves in a way that makes life on a mobile device easier, and arguably the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; version of that site. At the very least, desktop and mobile should be equals in content and access, while having individual design decisions that emphasize the strengths of the platform. BarhamInk.com is designed with these principles in mind. Anything that you can find easily on desktop, you can find just as easily on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-accessibility&quot;&gt;A Note on Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typography and readability are to 2013 (or so) as Accessibility is to 2018 (or so). In the intervening years, Apple has made significant efforts in their products to account for people of all abilities to enjoy them. I’d like to be doing the same here.  My first step was to increase text size and contrast and to include alt-text on all images. The work of writers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stevensblog.co&quot;&gt;Steven Aquino&lt;/a&gt; have helped me to understand that this should be an area of concern for all designers. If you find anything on the site that makes reading it unnecessarily difficult for certain people, please &lt;a href=&quot;nate.barham@gmail.com&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard about Jekyll from Matt Gemmell. It’s a static website generator that for my purposes, does three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gives full control of HTML and CSS styling
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Squarespace allowed some customization, but every template I tried had dependencies and corner cases where the site just never looked the way I wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tumblr had more control in this way; however, the platform itself was not designed for hosting websites like BarhamInk.com and Think Critical always felt shoehorned into a community where it didn’t belong.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes everything load &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; faster
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Both previous sites, and especially the Squarespace version, were inexplicably (at least to me and other laypersons) slow to load. It’s a site with some text and a few images. Why a four or five second load time?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jekyll uses static pages, which ends up meaning that loading the site is down to a small fraction of a second on a fast connection, and even when the connection is slow, the text and structure loads quickly while the images appear as they download.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows me to write in Markdown
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now, this is definitely not an exclusive feature, but as I use Ulysses to write novels, I’ve become very attached to Markdown syntax in my writing. Years ago, I attempted to get Marco Arment’s Second Crack working because I was attracted to the idea of typing up a plaintext Markdown document, dropping it into a folder, and having that post appear on my website. No Tumblr app needed, no Squarespace blog app needed, no visiting a web interface to post—just my words in the simplest file format possible and a folder that syncs.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jekyll gets most of the way there, though it does require a push to the host. Maybe now that the site is in action, I’ll be able to find a way to just drop content into a folder and watch it appear.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve made it this far, bravo! And I thank you. This site redesign has been an obsessive labor of love only equaled by the amount of focus I spend on the paperback versions of my books. Unfortunately I am not nearly as adept with HTML/CSS as I am with a descriptive paragraph or dialogue, but I hope my efforts make using the site more pleasant and reflect the attention to detail that I try to apply to all of my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Nate&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to the redesigned BarhamInk.com, the new home for Alora’s Tear and other writings by me, Nathan Barham. For most people, the take away is this: it’s fast! Like, really fast. Even if you’re on a limited mobile connection, BarhamInk.com should be one of the fastest sites you visit on any given day. And despite the speed increase, all of the content, features, and capabilities from the old site are still here (plus a lot more). If you’ve been following the book series since its debut in 2014 or if you’ve been following my writing on Apple, gaming, and other interests, you’ll notice more changes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Critically Speaking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critically Speaking" /><published>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically%20Speaking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html">&lt;p&gt;While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast &lt;em&gt;Critically Speaking&lt;/em&gt; which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;ShoutEngine&lt;/a&gt; if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise has us taking on a piece of videogames journalism each week, looking for meaning and providing commentary on the state of the industry. In addition, we talk about our current obsessions in gaming and generally laugh and have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, each episode has components that are evergreen and some that are very dated. Scott is hilarious and worth a listen just for his spontaneous accents, and the recording production quality is quite high, mostly thanks to our producer/editor Ryan Taylor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the trip down memory lane at your own (quite minimal) risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;Critically Speaking with Nate Barham and Scott Boren&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast Critically Speaking which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at ShoutEngine if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apple Software is like Windows Hardware</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple-Software-is-like-Windows-Hardware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple Software is like Windows Hardware" /><published>2018-04-07T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple%20Software%20is%20like%20Windows%20Hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple-Software-is-like-Windows-Hardware.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been on a committee at work to select a Windows touchscreen laptop. We’ve tested a number of machines, and it’s only served to reinforce what I already knew to be true: most mainstream Windows hardware is trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. That’s a bit too harsh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Windows hardware can be ok, but it never feels cohesive. There’s always something that feels janky at best and downright awful more often than not. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any piece of Windows hardware comes from multiple vendors (as does Apple’s, but there’s a different level of quality control happening there): the trackpad feels disconnected from the UI or has flimsy buttons or strange scrolling behavior or unreliable tap and drag functionality or sketchy multi-finger gestures. And, even if the rest of the computer works and feels like a nice machine, the trackpad feels like a car that’s had the matching rims stolen and replaced with bicycle tires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same can be said for touchscreen materials and behaviors, keyboards (including key layouts!), fingerprint readers, charging solutions, hinges, speakers, and so on. On every machine, there’s at least one (usually a couple) that come from a subcontractor and more importantly feel like they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that these machines are a hodgepodge of commodity components slapped together into a box cheap enough that customers will buy it based on one of its better qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough bashing of Windows machines. Let’s get to the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years Apple software seems to have the reputation of being in decline. I’m not here to say one way or another, but I have noticed that Apple software has become increasingly like the Windows hardware described above—a hodgepodge of components that against all odds seems to work most of the time (less and less often as time goes by).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that software in general is a clever illusion built atop a cacophony of Rube Goldberg machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Apple’s case the poster child for this theory is Siri. Each of its features, while intriguing and even impressive in some cases when they work, don’t function as a coherent whole. Context works, sometimes. But not when referring to certain topics. Trivia works, in a few particular domains. Apps can use Siri, but only specific types, and even then with bizarre results and incoherent behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing is, it’s not only Siri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MacOS has slowly been working its way toward the same state: tags, tabs, back to the Mac visuals and their removal, iOS influenced app designs, apps that live mostly in the Menu Bar, Save As, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WatchOS for sure has the problem, with its first gen apps versus newer versions versus companies discontinuing their WatchOS apps altogether, the honeycomb launcher, differing notification types, and a somewhat confused mixed interaction model (touch, force-press, crown).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even iOS has come to this with different behaviors on different phone models (and iPad models) and legacy apps that haven’t been updated for recent hardware like the iPhone X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile Apple’s hardware has none of these problems. Oh, it has problems of course (I’m looking at you, ever worsening butterfly key switch situation) but even when it does, the user never gets the sense that it is because the components aren’t from the same company. At least on hardware, users get the sense that it’s all from Apple, and any issue is due to a mistake in the design rather than assuming that the keyboard sucks because they cheaped out and bought a component from a lesser subcontractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately with software it increasingly &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; as if there are at best multiple Apple software companies that all do things a little differently from one another, and at worst that even under the umbrella of one product, the components of that software are made by entirely different companies with different priorities, and severely differing quality levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this is the case, the whole product suffers and likely gives the user a lackluster experience when things go right, and a broken, miserable experience when they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve recently been on a committee at work to select a Windows touchscreen laptop. We’ve tested a number of machines, and it’s only served to reinforce what I already knew to be true: most mainstream Windows hardware is trash.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Guest Post on Helheimen Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guest Post on Helheimen Design" /><published>2016-08-07T08:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-07T08:05:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design.html">&lt;p&gt;My brilliant cover artist, Isis Sousa, asked me to write a &lt;a href=&quot;http://helheimendesign.blogspot.no/2016/08/aloras-tear-vol-iii-locations-guest.html&quot;&gt;guest post for her blog&lt;/a&gt; concerning the work we did on Volume III. Now, when I say &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt;, I mean &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt;, since the real magic happens on her side, while I pester her about the details: a slightly different shade here, a smirk instead of a smile, a new armor texture, none of which I could implement myself (seriously, it would be awful), but all of which she somehow manages to get just right before we are finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She and I once had a conversation about how my descriptions of Vladvir reminded her of Norway (where she lives). I told her that the mountains, forests, and grasslands were all based on the Northwest United States, and mostly northern Idaho. Only in Vladvir, everything is much bigger. She sent back some photos of a vacation or hike she and her husband had taken. Sure enough, Norway looks a lot like the mountains of northern Idaho, only everything is more exaggerated. It was indeed like looking at pictures of a real life Vladvir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the guest post, we decided that the places in each of the covers and some of the notable locations in the books were a good topic for discussion. More specifically, the connection these fictional places have to the real ones I’ve been lucky enough to live near or visit. So head over to her site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://helheimendesign.blogspot.no/2016/08/aloras-tear-vol-iii-locations-guest.html&quot;&gt;Helheimen Design&lt;/a&gt;, and have a look.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">My brilliant cover artist, Isis Sousa, asked me to write a guest post for her blog concerning the work we did on Volume III. Now, when I say we, I mean she, since the real magic happens on her side, while I pester her about the details: a slightly different shade here, a smirk instead of a smile, a new armor texture, none of which I could implement myself (seriously, it would be awful), but all of which she somehow manages to get just right before we are finished.</summary></entry></feed>