<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-18T11:38:57-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Barham Ink</title><subtitle>Publishing</subtitle><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><entry><title type="html">Volume IV Title</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volume IV Title" /><published>2018-06-15T11:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-15T11:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2018/06/15/Volume-IV-Title.html">&lt;p&gt;This summer, the second trilogy in the &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; series begins. For today, let’s start with the title to book four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Alora's Tear, Volume IV:&lt;br /&gt;
Circlets and Seekers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you’ve read the Epilogue to &lt;em&gt;The Voice like Water&lt;/em&gt;. I’m so excited to share this story with everyone. Check back for more details, back cover text, excerpt, and of course the fantastic cover art!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">This summer, the second trilogy in the Alora’s Tear series begins. For today, let’s start with the title to book four.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Site Design 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site Design 2018" /><published>2018-06-14T01:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-14T01:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing/2018/06/14/Site-Design-2018.html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the redesigned &lt;a href=&quot;http://barhamink.com&quot;&gt;BarhamInk.com&lt;/a&gt;, the new home for &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; and other writings by me, Nathan Barham. For most people, the take away is this: it’s fast! Like, really fast. Even if you’re on a limited mobile connection, BarhamInk.com should be one of the fastest sites you visit on any given day. And despite the speed increase, all of the content, features, and capabilities from the old site are still here (plus a lot more). If you’ve been following the book series since its debut in 2014 or if you’ve been following my writing on Apple, gaming, and other interests, you’ll notice more changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, where once there were two sites, now there is only one. When I began writing &lt;a href=&quot;natebarham.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Think Critical&lt;/a&gt; (at natebarham.com) my goal was simply to share my thoughts about technology and gaming, two interests that have been a part of my life for as long as I can remember. I hosted the site with Tumblr, and though it never really fit the trademark Tumblr aesthetic, there was enough customization that I could make the site look and behave almost exactly as I envisioned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014 I published &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear: Fragments&lt;/em&gt;, and with it, BarhamInk.com on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.squarespace.com&quot;&gt;Squarespace&lt;/a&gt;. This solution allowed me to focus on content first, things like &lt;a href=&quot;/locations/&quot;&gt;important locations&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;/pronunciation/&quot;&gt;pronunciation guide&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;/writing/2014/07/18/Writing-Process/&quot;&gt;thoughts on writing&lt;/a&gt;. Not to mention links for buying books and information about the new publishing entity I’d just created. Secondarily, Squarespace provided easy design templates to work with that didn’t require CSS or HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward several years—and four novels. Things have changed. Now everything points to BarhamInk.com, one site to communicate my thoughts on various subjects as well as promote and enrich the world of Vladvir, its characters, and any future worlds when Askon and friends turn their final page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who have seen all the iterations of my online writing presence, I thank you especially. Without the readers of Think Critical, I might not have felt confident enough to publish &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; on my own. And for those who have always followed the books but never knew about the site that came before, it is my hope that you will enjoy having a more complete picture of the &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt; who crafted Askon’s tale and all the tales yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Technical site details follow, if you’re into that sort of thing…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;readability&quot;&gt;Readability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of years ago I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://practicaltypography.com&quot;&gt;Butterick’s Practical Typography&lt;/a&gt;. It was the first formal consolidation of all the typography principles I was seeing applied across many of my favorite sites on the web, some of which are still actively maintained today (&lt;a href=&quot;http://brooksreview.net&quot;&gt;The Brooks Review&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattgemmell.com&quot;&gt;MattGemmell.com&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://inessential.com&quot;&gt;Inessential&lt;/a&gt; by Brent Simmons, &lt;a href=&quot;http://macstories.net&quot;&gt;MacStories&lt;/a&gt;, and many others). I used these principles in designing the paperback versions of &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; and have done so on BarhamInk.com as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of device, text should be large, clear and high contrast, with ample whitespace between lines and surrounding the content, while line length balances screen size with typeface size, never extending so far that they become tiring for readers. These details alone aim to make a better reading experience whether you’re visiting for a chapter-length excerpt or a blog post of a few dozen words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The featured typeface is Quattrocento (in its serif and sans versions) to characterize the site’s text in a way that suggests both general purpose writing and medieval fantasy (when reading Vladvir-related content). If you block web fonts, you’ll get Palatino, Garamond, or just plain old serif. And, because I was too attached to it, despite examining dozens of alternatives, Adelle makes its way over from Think Critical for the site title courtesy of TypeKit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links and headings take on my favorite shade of green (Askon’s signature cloak is the same color for both practical and sentimental reasons), differentiating them from body text and navigation links. All links take on the underline text decoration when you hover over them with the cursor. Pretty standard, of course, but intentional nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;images&quot;&gt;Images&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images take on several forms, most notably the large, highly detailed art from &lt;a href=&quot;http://artstation.com/isissousa&quot;&gt;Isis Sousa&lt;/a&gt;, whose work is as much a part of the &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; series as are my words. These big beautiful digital paintings take center stage, setting the tone for each volume’s preview page. Inside posts, images are smaller and can flow alongside the text on the desktop or tablet, while remaining inline on phone screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigation&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigation links are persistent across the site,but do not follow the reader (I despise sites that do this) as they scroll down the page. On desktop, each category has the ability to show a dropdown submenu for more options. For instance, the about section has a dropdown for The Author, Barham Ink, and The Site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On mobile, there’s one link to buy books and a menu that takes readers to the main sections of the site, the submenu links from the desktop dropdown are provided above the content so mobile users don’t miss out on any of the content suggestions from the desktop version. Lastly, a second set of navigation appears below the featured image on book buying pages to highlight the places where you can purchase &lt;em&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/em&gt; in paperback and ebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;responsive-design&quot;&gt;Responsive Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world where most people consider their phone to be their primary computer (even if they don’t know it consciously) websites should present themselves in a way that makes life on a mobile device easier, and arguably the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; version of that site. At the very least, desktop and mobile should be equals in content and access, while having individual design decisions that emphasize the strengths of the platform. BarhamInk.com is designed with these principles in mind. Anything that you can find easily on desktop, you can find just as easily on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-accessibility&quot;&gt;A Note on Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typography and readability are to 2013 (or so) as Accessibility is to 2018 (or so). In the intervening years, Apple has made significant efforts in their products to account for people of all abilities to enjoy them. I’d like to be doing the same here.  My first step was to increase text size and contrast and to include alt-text on all images. The work of writers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stevensblog.co&quot;&gt;Steven Aquino&lt;/a&gt; have helped me to understand that this should be an area of concern for all designers. If you find anything on the site that makes reading it unnecessarily difficult for certain people, please &lt;a href=&quot;nate.barham@gmail.com&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard about Jekyll from Matt Gemmell. It’s a static website generator that for my purposes, does three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gives full control of HTML and CSS styling
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Squarespace allowed some customization, but every template I tried had dependencies and corner cases where the site just never looked the way I wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tumblr had more control in this way; however, the platform itself was not designed for hosting websites like BarhamInk.com and Think Critical always felt shoehorned into a community where it didn’t belong.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes everything load &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; faster
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Both previous sites, and especially the Squarespace version, were inexplicably (at least to me and other laypersons) slow to load. It’s a site with some text and a few images. Why a four or five second load time?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jekyll uses static pages, which ends up meaning that loading the site is down to a small fraction of a second on a fast connection, and even when the connection is slow, the text and structure loads quickly while the images appear as they download.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allows me to write in Markdown
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now, this is definitely not an exclusive feature, but as I use Ulysses to write novels, I’ve become very attached to Markdown syntax in my writing. Years ago, I attempted to get Marco Arment’s Second Crack working because I was attracted to the idea of typing up a plaintext Markdown document, dropping it into a folder, and having that post appear on my website. No Tumblr app needed, no Squarespace blog app needed, no visiting a web interface to post—just my words in the simplest file format possible and a folder that syncs.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jekyll gets most of the way there, though it does require a push to the host. Maybe now that the site is in action, I’ll be able to find a way to just drop content into a folder and watch it appear.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve made it this far, bravo! And I thank you. This site redesign has been an obsessive labor of love only equaled by the amount of focus I spend on the paperback versions of my books. Unfortunately I am not nearly as adept with HTML/CSS as I am with a descriptive paragraph or dialogue, but I hope my efforts make using the site more pleasant and reflect the attention to detail that I try to apply to all of my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Nate&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to the redesigned BarhamInk.com, the new home for Alora’s Tear and other writings by me, Nathan Barham. For most people, the take away is this: it’s fast! Like, really fast. Even if you’re on a limited mobile connection, BarhamInk.com should be one of the fastest sites you visit on any given day. And despite the speed increase, all of the content, features, and capabilities from the old site are still here (plus a lot more). If you’ve been following the book series since its debut in 2014 or if you’ve been following my writing on Apple, gaming, and other interests, you’ll notice more changes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Critically Speaking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critically Speaking" /><published>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically%20Speaking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/gaming/2018/06/04/Critically-Speaking.html">&lt;p&gt;While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast &lt;em&gt;Critically Speaking&lt;/em&gt; which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;ShoutEngine&lt;/a&gt; if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise has us taking on a piece of videogames journalism each week, looking for meaning and providing commentary on the state of the industry. In addition, we talk about our current obsessions in gaming and generally laugh and have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, each episode has components that are evergreen and some that are very dated. Scott is hilarious and worth a listen just for his spontaneous accents, and the recording production quality is quite high, mostly thanks to our producer/editor Ryan Taylor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the trip down memory lane at your own (quite minimal) risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shoutengine.com/CriticallySpeaking/&quot;&gt;Critically Speaking with Nate Barham and Scott Boren&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">While rebuilding BarhamInk.com, I came across the now defunct podcast Critically Speaking which I hosted with Scott Boren. The full 42 episode run of the show is still available at ShoutEngine if for some reason, you’re interested in listening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Critically Speaking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple-Software-is-like-Windows-Hardware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critically Speaking" /><published>2018-04-07T05:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T05:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple%20Software%20is%20like%20Windows%20Hardware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple/2018/04/07/Apple-Software-is-like-Windows-Hardware.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been on a committee at work to select a Windows touchscreen laptop. We’ve tested a number of machines, and it’s only served to reinforce what I already knew to be true: most mainstream Windows hardware is trash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. That’s a bit too harsh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Windows hardware can be ok, but it never feels cohesive. There’s always something that feels janky at best and downright awful more often than not. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any piece of Windows hardware comes from multiple vendors (as does Apple’s, but there’s a different level of quality control happening there): the trackpad feels disconnected from the UI or has flimsy buttons or strange scrolling behavior or unreliable tap and drag functionality or sketchy multi-finger gestures. And, even if the rest of the computer works and feels like a nice machine, the trackpad feels like a car that’s had the matching rims stolen and replaced with bicycle tires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same can be said for touchscreen materials and behaviors, keyboards (including key layouts!), fingerprint readers, charging solutions, hinges, speakers, and so on. On every machine, there’s at least one (usually a couple) that come from a subcontractor and more importantly feel like they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that these machines are a hodgepodge of commodity components slapped together into a box cheap enough that customers will buy it based on one of its better qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough bashing of Windows machines. Let’s get to the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years Apple software seems to have the reputation of being in decline. I’m not here to say one way or another, but I have noticed that Apple software has become increasingly like the Windows hardware described above—a hodgepodge of components that against all odds seems to work most of the time (less and less often as time goes by).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that software in general is a clever illusion built atop a cacophony of Rube Goldberg machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Apple’s case the poster child for this theory is Siri. Each of its features, while intriguing and even impressive in some cases when they work, don’t function as a coherent whole. Context works, sometimes. But not when referring to certain topics. Trivia works, in a few particular domains. Apps can use Siri, but only specific types, and even then with bizarre results and incoherent behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing is, it’s not only Siri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MacOS has slowly been working its way toward the same state: tags, tabs, back to the Mac visuals and their removal, iOS influenced app designs, apps that live mostly in the Menu Bar, Save As, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WatchOS for sure has the problem, with its first gen apps versus newer versions versus companies discontinuing their WatchOS apps altogether, the honeycomb launcher, differing notification types, and a somewhat confused mixed interaction model (touch, force-press, crown).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even iOS has come to this with different behaviors on different phone models (and iPad models) and legacy apps that haven’t been updated for recent hardware like the iPhone X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile Apple’s hardware has none of these problems. Oh, it has problems of course (I’m looking at you, ever worsening butterfly key switch situation) but even when it does, the user never gets the sense that it is because the components aren’t from the same company. At least on hardware, users get the sense that it’s all from Apple, and any issue is due to a mistake in the design rather than assuming that the keyboard sucks because they cheaped out and bought a component from a lesser subcontractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately with software it increasingly &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; as if there are at best multiple Apple software companies that all do things a little differently from one another, and at worst that even under the umbrella of one product, the components of that software are made by entirely different companies with different priorities, and severely differing quality levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this is the case, the whole product suffers and likely gives the user a lackluster experience when things go right, and a broken, miserable experience when they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve recently been on a committee at work to select a Windows touchscreen laptop. We’ve tested a number of machines, and it’s only served to reinforce what I already knew to be true: most mainstream Windows hardware is trash.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Guest Post on Helheimen Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guest Post on Helheimen Design" /><published>2016-08-07T08:05:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-07T08:05:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/08/07/Guest-Post-on-Helheimen-Design.html">&lt;p&gt;My brilliant cover artist, Isis Sousa, asked me to write a &lt;a href=&quot;http://helheimendesign.blogspot.no/2016/08/aloras-tear-vol-iii-locations-guest.html&quot;&gt;guest post for her blog&lt;/a&gt; concerning the work we did on Volume III. Now, when I say &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt;, I mean &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt;, since the real magic happens on her side, while I pester her about the details: a slightly different shade here, a smirk instead of a smile, a new armor texture, none of which I could implement myself (seriously, it would be awful), but all of which she somehow manages to get just right before we are finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She and I once had a conversation about how my descriptions of Vladvir reminded her of Norway (where she lives). I told her that the mountains, forests, and grasslands were all based on the Northwest United States, and mostly northern Idaho. Only in Vladvir, everything is much bigger. She sent back some photos of a vacation or hike she and her husband had taken. Sure enough, Norway looks a lot like the mountains of northern Idaho, only everything is more exaggerated. It was indeed like looking at pictures of a real life Vladvir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the guest post, we decided that the places in each of the covers and some of the notable locations in the books were a good topic for discussion. More specifically, the connection these fictional places have to the real ones I’ve been lucky enough to live near or visit. So head over to her site, &lt;a href=&quot;http://helheimendesign.blogspot.no/2016/08/aloras-tear-vol-iii-locations-guest.html&quot;&gt;Helheimen Design&lt;/a&gt;, and have a look.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">My brilliant cover artist, Isis Sousa, asked me to write a guest post for her blog concerning the work we did on Volume III. Now, when I say we, I mean she, since the real magic happens on her side, while I pester her about the details: a slightly different shade here, a smirk instead of a smile, a new armor texture, none of which I could implement myself (seriously, it would be awful), but all of which she somehow manages to get just right before we are finished.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Equilibrium</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple/2016/07/17/Equilibrium.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Equilibrium" /><published>2016-07-17T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-17T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple/2016/07/17/Equilibrium</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple/2016/07/17/Equilibrium.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s 1997 and I’ve just researched and configured the best PC I can imagine for what was then a reasonable price. The beast, an ominous black tower in a world of boring beige, has a CPU ten times faster than the Packard Bell it’s replacing. It runs a new technology called AGP, which the sales person assures me is not only as good as the popular PCI solution but better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long story short, that guy was either a liar or an idiot. The lie plagued my perception of that PC from the very start and fueled an imbalance that may only now be coming to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, from that point forward there was always something incredible right around the corner. At first, it was a new PC that would be powerful enough to run the games I wanted to play at the time (AGP wasn’t upgradable, and the built-in card was starved for video memory, a critically important spec back then).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it was a laptop that felt like a real computer and not a hamstrung hack attempting the future before its time. I used some laptops (IBM, Compaq, HP) but didn’t pursue buying. I found that dream laptop (excuse me, notebook) in a Titanium PowerBook G4, ever after referred to affectionately as the TiBook. It had a trackpad that worked as advertised, a widescreen display, an operating system that looked modern, even futuristic without looking like a neon sign in Vegas, and that beautifully designed case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery life was good for the time, but not great in practical use. It was powerful, but buying or building a desktop with visibly more power was still easy and relatively cheap. And so the balance favored the future again, and I waited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to my notebook-that-feels-like-a-desktop came with a Penryn Macbook Pro. It even played PC games of the time at respectable frame rates using Boot Camp. That machine, to this day is probably my favorite computer. I wrote my first novel on it, played countless hours of World of Warcraft, edited the first videos of my daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the imbalance came again. Despite its power, mobility grew more important. Lighter, thinner, better battery life, the list that lay just around the corner. A Macbook Air came next, and now a Macbook, tiny and light, powerful enough to do all that I want these days on my work computer, and the most beautifully designed notebook I’ve ever seen (good luck topping this one, Jony).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’d traded performance for portability, so I built a gaming PC between the time of the stalwart Macbook Pro and the Macbook Air: my for-fun computer. It is fast and powerful, even today, and with a reasonable upgrade to the GPU, runs current games at another of those ever-retreating corners I’ve been waiting so long to turn, 1080p 60fps. Consoles haven’t truly done it yet, and look to be making the jump to 4k before they get the chance. As for me, I look at the 4k televisions in stores and see very little real world difference between them and my 1080p plasma, unlike with Retina where the difference achieved another past-fantasy tech milestone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that gets us to my point. I’ve reached a point of equilibrium in tech. Light, powerful, beautiful notebook, check (then do the same for TV display, set-top box, sound system, gaming PC, tablet, phone, even a smartwatch). With all of this amazing hardware, and the always evolving (usually improving) software, there are so few real world corners left to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always a new iPhone on the horizon, of course, a new everything. For the first time, however, none of it feels particularly pressing. Nothing feels like “Oh, if I only had a machine that would…” at this point. The last two items on my list were 1080p 60fps and an instantly responding Apple Watch (which, though I don’t have it yet, seems to be the real deal with WatchOS 3). It’s a somewhat peaceful and somewhat empty feeling, as if a part of me dissolved without my permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out there, some will shout “VR!” and “Self-driving cars!” and whatever else. I’ve tried VR, and it’s an interesting curiosity. I’m intrigued by a self-driving car, but the corner to turn for that one seems years away, maybe a decade, and that’s not considering the fact that a teacher’s salary is extremely unlikely to pay for one in the first — or second — phase (even the 30k Tesla Model 3 is priced beyond that, and that’s with virtually no autonomous features, or at least not the impressive, world changing ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for now, and possibly the first time since I was 13 or 14, the world of technology seems good enough. Can it get better? Always, and I fully expect it to. Will I want some new shiny thing come September, probably, but if Apple released nothing, just went totally dark, I’d be fine, and not in the sense that I’d survive, but in the sense that I wouldn’t feel compelled to ask for anything more. This 6S performs brilliantly in every measure I can think of. Ditto for all my other current devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose the most difficult part of balance is maintaining it. Perhaps that’s the new question. Is that next reveal enough to tip the scales? Is there something out there that’s coming up next that completes an imagined technological picture you have for yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, for now — for once — the answer is “No.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">It’s 1997 and I’ve just researched and configured the best PC I can imagine for what was then a reasonable price. The beast, an ominous black tower in a world of boring beige, has a CPU ten times faster than the Packard Bell it’s replacing. It runs a new technology called AGP, which the sales person assures me is not only as good as the popular PCI solution but better.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Puck (or why I support Bernie Sanders)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/politics/2016/05/21/The-Puck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Puck (or why I support Bernie Sanders)" /><published>2016-05-21T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-21T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/politics/2016/05/21/The-Puck</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/politics/2016/05/21/The-Puck.html">&lt;p&gt;Before I begin: If you support Bernie by harassing women or other public figures, attacking Hillary Clinton with sexist language and the tactics of the vile Gamergate or other foul misogynist hate groups, I am not your friend. I am not your ally, nor are you mine. You are a scourge that needs silencing and a pestilence in need of a cure. Stop this nonsense immediately and stand with the rest of us — for something — not against something in a thinly veiled attempt to justify your hate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following thoughts arose from a number of conservative family members asking why I support Bernie Sanders. For some time I’ve wanted to write a post encapsulating my decision and continued position. This is my response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a clear-thinking, educated person, I understand where the money for a progressive agenda would have to come from. I understand that I would pay more to the system in hopes of saving money elsewhere and to help those who need it most. These values are not foolish, ill conceived, or even unrealistic. I am not some hoodwinked, moony-eyed youth, dazzled by the allure of free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not make these decisions lightly but with the most concerted of efforts to fully understand my own position foremost, and those of others so as to not be blind to the faults of my own choice (and there are several) or the virtues of others’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, a few principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our government should help those who need help, and all people should have a truly equal chance. The US healthcare system is a blight that needs to be eradicated, replaced with an alternative reflecting the modern world and not a profit machine fueled by illness and misfortune. I respect those who fight for a noble cause, even when it is not popular. Only the people should be able to affect elections, not large corporate donations and backdoor deals. Our voting system — the key component to the greatness of our country — is broken, designed to punish the powerless and reward the powerful when it should simply count each person and their singular vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not support dividing everyone’s income to the point at which we are all paid the same. That scenario would be communist. Some have earned an easier life by sacrifice, and some have earned a harder one. If socialism means balancing the scales so that the American dream — that pursuit of a better life through hard work can result in success for any person willing to do said work — can be real again, then I am indeed for socialism. But I have always (even when I voted for Bush in 2000) insisted that our government exists to work for us, and that we pay into it for the services it can provide, be it roads and bridges, education, a military to protect us (though only as a last resort), or with clean, efficient energy, and a healthcare system that helps everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched as a corrupt insurance industry and profit-driven medical industry depleted my Grandparents’ savings while my Grandfather struggled with the horror of dementia and my Grandmother struggled as her partner of five decades fought against that horror. And it only got worse as his condition got worse. It turns my stomach to think of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look into my son’s bleeding face (he fell and bumped his chin on the bed) I am ashamed that even one of my first thoughts is given to the bill and not to his pain or fear. Every thought should go to him. This too turns my stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we generate all of this prosperity if we must live in fear that it will be swept away by random chance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some events are unavoidable. But if our government is going to pay for something with the taxes they extract from us, let it be this. And the most embarrassing part for our nation is that other countries have already solved this problem. The systems vary, and none are perfect, but they are all more effective and far less expensive than ours. This is the issue for which I feel the most passionate, partial measures will not do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In high school I read Wayne Gretzky’s biography, and one quote stood out (a quote I also appreciated much later when Steve Jobs reiterated it). He said, “I skate to where the puck is going, not to where it has been.” I began then to apply this philosophy to my political views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a hundred years, a thousand, will the greatest country on Earth help its people when they are sick, or will it watch them suffer as their life savings is instantly consumed and they worry about money when they should be focusing on those for whom they care most? After examining all of my politics under this lens, I saw what I would someday want in a politician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, about a years ago, I read about Bernie Sanders. Nearly all of his policies pass my self-imposed test. In a hundred, a thousand years will we: restrict people based on their gender, race, or sexual orientation? Listen to them instead of saying that the problem is already solved? Power our industry and personal lives cleanly and efficiently or in whatever way is most profitable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will we be at war with a world full of enemies, or will we have found solutions to render those enemies ineffectual and irrelevant — or even have managed to make them into allies? Will we pride ourselves in the education of our people — so much so that we would pay to make certain that they are all educated? Will we, the people, decide what steps our government takes, making sure that it acts in our interests and not in the interests of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, will we still remain at the whims of capitalist industry, which though it has served us well, has clear flaws that concentrate wealth and power at the top, while continuously forcing those at the bottom further and further down? Will we shout insults, build walls, and shoot first, asking questions later like fearful cavemen (or women) cowering in the dark, paranoid of everyone and everything that is not like us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, will we apathetically accept that the world cannot be changed, that our lives, and the lives of those whose are the hardest, cannot be improved? Will we reach for half-loves and smile when given our quarter portion? Will we deal and barter with swindlers who already have more than they and a dozen generations of their descendants could ever use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many of our major victories as a people came from skating to where the puck was going, to where the world was going. The pilgrims who crossed the Atlantic did. The revolutionaries did. Lincoln did with the emancipation. When we awoke to Hitler and the Japanese, when women won the right to vote, when the Civil Rights Act was passed, when Neil Armstrong landed on the moon, we skated to where the world was going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we know this only in hindsight. Now, today, we must choose to the best of our abilities where we think the puck will go. Bernie Sanders aims for where I think the puck will be. I support him because I want all of us to be there, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Before I begin: If you support Bernie by harassing women or other public figures, attacking Hillary Clinton with sexist language and the tactics of the vile Gamergate or other foul misogynist hate groups, I am not your friend. I am not your ally, nor are you mine. You are a scourge that needs silencing and a pestilence in need of a cure. Stop this nonsense immediately and stand with the rest of us — for something — not against something in a thinly veiled attempt to justify your hate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Official Facebook Page</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publishing,/alora's/tear/2016/05/03/Official-Facebook-Page.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Official Facebook Page" /><published>2016-05-03T09:34:38-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-03T09:34:38-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publishing,/alora's/tear/2016/05/03/Official-Facebook-Page</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publishing,/alora's/tear/2016/05/03/Official-Facebook-Page.html">&lt;p&gt;After two books and quite a bit of procrastination, Barham Ink and &lt;i&gt;Alora’s Tear&lt;/i&gt; finally have an &lt;a href=&quot;http://facebook.com/barhamink&quot;&gt;official home on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;. As with anything related to my writing, thanks so much for the support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every like, every share, every reader counts. Let’s see how many we can get! The more people follow this page, the easier it becomes to justify this wonderful second job of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check back there (or here on BarhamInk.com) for upcoming events, signings, readings, and soon a proper look at Isis Sousa’s fantastic art and design for Alora’s Tear, Volume III: The Voice like Water.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">After two books and quite a bit of procrastination, Barham Ink and Alora’s Tear finally have an official home on Facebook. As with anything related to my writing, thanks so much for the support.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Signed Copies on Etsy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/05/02/Signed-Copies-on-Etsy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Signed Copies on Etsy" /><published>2016-05-02T13:50:59-07:00</published><updated>2016-05-02T13:50:59-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/05/02/Signed-Copies-on-Etsy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/alora's/tear/2016/05/02/Signed-Copies-on-Etsy.html">&lt;p&gt;Starting this week (yesterday, actually) signed, hand wrapped copies of &lt;i&gt;Fragments&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;The Elf and the Arrow&lt;/i&gt; are again available for purchase, now through the Barham Ink shop on Etsy. Prior sales went through a different provider which meant higher prices and shipping costs, and that only one book or the other  could be offered for sale at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new shop and Etsy’s sales policy allow prices to be lower than ever without reducing the amount each sale generates toward production on the next book. Shipping is also cheaper and more accurate thanks to Etsy’s automatically calculated shipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/shop/BarhamInk&quot;&gt;Check out the shop&lt;/a&gt;—the new prices—and as always, share, like, and tell your friends.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Starting this week (yesterday, actually) signed, hand wrapped copies of Fragments and The Elf and the Arrow are again available for purchase, now through the Barham Ink shop on Etsy. Prior sales went through a different provider which meant higher prices and shipping costs, and that only one book or the other  could be offered for sale at any given time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Social Pressures of being “Right”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-Right.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Social Pressures of being &quot;Right&quot;" /><published>2016-04-24T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-04-24T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-%22Right%22</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apple,/politics/2016/04/24/The-Social-Pressures-of-Being-Right.html">&lt;p&gt;Do you like Apple’s Retina MacBook? Do you still enjoy wearing an Apple Watch every day? Maybe you like the look of Tesla’s upcoming Model 3 or use your iPad Pro as a full-fledged computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop me if you’ve heard this one before, but you’re wrong. Wrong for liking things that others don’t, wrong for attempting to understand where these designs and products are coming from rather than critiquing the obvious compromises they’ve made or the places where they’ve actually chosen to diverge from the herd, wrong, wrong, wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe wrong, as long as the future plays out a certain way and those spouting constant criticism turn out to be right (even a broken clock…). And what is right? Is it vindication in finding a MacBook five years from now that’s much faster and has much better battery life? If so, the great online advisors can claim the win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“See, we told you v1 was underpowered and had terrible battery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, “See, we told you that Tesla would have to change that no-grille design if they wanted to sell more cars.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem is, they have merely predicted the inevitable. Computers will get faster, cars will have different visual touches, tablet operating systems will become more capable. Meanwhile, many must sit back and watch as the collective club nods sagely at each other for fear of ending up being the one who was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For being the one who liked Apple Watch 1.0, they will suffer the future torment of “I told you so.” And then won’t they feel dumb? After all, isn’t the most important thing to appear smart? Turns out (TM), you can be smart and disagree with the crowd. You can be insightful, and not correctly predict the future. And more essentially, simply by offering a different viewpoint, you can create a much more interesting discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I encouraging vehement Mac vs. PC era arguments? No. Am I saying that the conventional wisdom of a few high profile voices is always wrong? No. But the discourse suffers from the fear of being in the out group, the fear of having a dissenting opinion. If we were all wrong a little more often, we’d have a much more varied conversation and foster inclusivity at a basic level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ll say it. I think all of these products are great, intriguing, and worthy of discussion from many viewpoints, not just criticisms of their most obvious compromises. And none of them are perfect. None are above criticism, but they are above only criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think the same, you should not be afraid to say so, because understanding why something is the way it is informs us of the reality in which we live and not a fantasy where we get to design a world we would prefer. After all, we don’t study the horse only to say that it is not a unicorn, and that if evolution (or deity) had only included a three-foot horn on the horse’s forehead, it would have been an acceptable creature. Instead we understand the beauty of the thing as it is, what evolutionary steps may have led to its current form, and maybe every so often wonder if the unicorn is out there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unicorn becomes part of the larger understanding, just as our wished-for versions of iOS or a Mac Pro with gaming GPUs should be a part. Speculate, certainly. Criticize, of course. But don’t forget that the larger part of the fun is to analyze and thus further understand the things we are interested in. Stop caving to the social pressure of being right. Be reasonable, be considerate, but worry more about appreciating the thing before leveling the same criticism that a half-dozen full-time pundits have already articulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ok. Appreciation is not equivalent to inferior intellect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nathan Barham</name></author><summary type="html">Do you like Apple’s Retina MacBook? Do you still enjoy wearing an Apple Watch every day? Maybe you like the look of Tesla’s upcoming Model 3 or use your iPad Pro as a full-fledged computer.</summary></entry></feed>